Kolb, Frances Arick. Papers, 1955-1990 (inclusive), 1972-1990 (bulk): A Finding Aid
Papers, 1955-1990 (inclusive), 1972-1990 (bulk)
MC 481
Schlesinger Library, Radcliffe Institute
Frances Arick Kolb
19 + 1/2 file boxes, 1 supersize folder, 1 photograph folder
Papers of Frances Arick Kolb, educational consultant, historian, and Eastern Regional Director and board member of the National Organization for Women.
Accession numbers: 89-M57, 91-M96, 91-M175, 95-M158
These papers were given to the Schlesinger Library by Frances Arick Kolb in March 1989. Additional papers were donated by Alfred Kolb in June and October 1991 and in November 1995.
TERMS OF USE
Access. Unrestricted except that access to folders #11.1-16.14 is governed by a legal agreement between NOW and the Schlesinger Library and requires the written permission of NOW. Folders #16.10-16.11 are restricted until January 1, 2040, except to those researchers with the written permission of the director of the Schlesinger Library.
BIOGRAPHY
Frances (Arick) Kolb, an educational consultant and historian, was born in 1937 in Worcester, Massachusetts. She attended Brandeis University from 1954 to 1956 before receiving her B.A. in history and secondary education from Washington University (1958), her master's degree in American civilization from the University of Pennsylvania (1959), and her Ph.D. in history from Washington University (1972). She was married to and divorced from Zivon Cohen. She later married Alfred Kolb; they had a daughter, Sharon.
FAK was an instructor in continuing education at Pennsylvania State University (1971-1973), an instructor in American history at the University of Pittsburgh (1973), assistant professor in the department of history at Montclair (New Jersey) State College (1973-1975), adjunct instructor in women's studies at City College, City University of New York (1974-1795), curriculum coordinator for the Training Institute for Sex Desegregation at Douglass College of Rutgers University (1975-1979), a training specialist for Project Inter-Action (1980-1981), and assistant director of The Network in Andover, Massachusetts (1982-?). In addition, FAK was a member of the Panel on Teaching Women's History at the American Historical Association's national conference (1975), chair of the Panel on Funding Women's Studies for the Berkshire Conference of Women Historians meeting at Bryn Mawr (June 1975), served on the planning committee of the Bicentennial Celebration on Women at Douglass College (March-April 1976), was a consultant and trainer for the Educational Improvement Center South of the New Jersey Department of Education (June-July 1978), and consultant and trainer for the New England Educational Equity Center (1979-1980).
Her positions within the National Organization for Women included founding member and member of the Board of Directors of the South Hills NOW Day Nursery School (1972-1973), Eastern Regional Director (1973-1975), and National Board member (1975-1977), where she served as NOW archivist. She was also on the Rules Committee of the 1975 and 1976 national conferences, was a member of the Budget Committee of the National Board, Finance Coordinator of the NOW Freedom Train (1976), chair of the NOW Arrangements Committee for the International Women's Year Conference (1977), and chair of the Economic Sanctions Committee of the ERA Strike Force (1977-1979).
FAK died of breast cancer January 12, 1991.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
This collection contains correspondence, clippings, research notes, printed material, audiocassettes, and writings by FAK, focusing mainly on her work in NOW and her research documenting the history of NOW. The records are arranged in seven series:
Series I, Personal and Biographical (#1.1-1.8), contains a resume, clippings, correspondence, and school transcripts. The records are arranged chronologically.
Series II, Articles and Speeches by FAK, (#1.9-2.4), contains correspondence, drafts, and copies of articles and speeches by FK. Subjects include NOW, women and psychoanalysis, Betty Friedan, Wilma Scott Heide, and Gloria Steinem.
Series III, "The National Organization for Women: From the Feminine Mystique to the National Movement, 1960-1974" (#2.5-10.24), contains research notes, drafts of text, and notes on interviews conducted by FAK with early NOW members for her unfinished book on NOW's history. The book, started in the late 1970s, was never completed, but there is at least a partial draft of every chapter. The series is divided into four subseries.
Subseries A, Correspondence (#2.5), contains correspondence relating to the grant under which the book was started.
Subseries B, Drafts (#2.6-6.5), contains various drafts of the book. Some of the drafts in the collection are hard copies made from disks by the Schlesinger Library staff, a process explained in the memo found in #2.6. The drafts are arranged with chapters from the same draft first followed by individual drafts in order of chapter number. There is no order within the chapters, since it is impossible to determine when the drafts were done.
Subseries C, Oral Histories (#6.6-6.13), contains detailed notes and interviewee lists from the oral histories FAK conducted with early NOW members. There is also correspondence with the interviewees concerning the amount and importance of information they might impart. Audiocassettes of the oral histories conducted by FAK are available to researchers as T-312. A list of those interviewed can be found in #6.9.
Subseries D, Research Notes (#6.14-10.24), contains handwritten notes arranged by topic in alphabetical order. Most of the research notes concern papers of other NOW members as well as NOW's organizational records found at the Schlesinger Library.
Series IV, NOW-Related (#11.1-16.14), contains correspondence, notes, printed material, clippings, etc., concerning FAK's role as Eastern Regional Director, national board member, and as a chapter member. A small number of files were created by Jacqueline Ceballos, who was Eastern Regional Director before FAK. The series is divided into seven subseries.
Subseries A, NOW General Correspondence (#11.1-11.4), contains correspondence concerning both Eastern Regional and national board issues. Correspondence found here is similar to that found in subseries B and C. The correspondence has been maintained in the order in which FAK kept it. Records are arranged chronologically.
Subseries B, Eastern Region (#11.5-13.11), contains correspondence, printed material, clippings, etc., concerning FAK's role as Eastern Regional Director as well as her later involvement with NOW New Jersey and Massachusetts NOW Materials are arranged chronologically, with individual chapter folders located at the end of the subseries.
Subseries C, NOW National Board (#13.12-14.3), contains correspondence and printed material concerning FAK's term as a member of the board. Records are arranged chronologically.
Subseries D, Equal Rights Amendment (#14.4-15.7), contains correspondence, financial records, printed material, etc., concerning the ERA Freedom Train and the NOW Economic Boycott, in both of which FAK held leadership roles. The NOW Economic Boycott records also include lists of supporters of the boycott, who encouraged organizations to refuse to hold conferences in states that had not ratified the ERA. Records are arranged chronologically.
Subseries E, Archives (15.8-16.2), contains correspondence and completed records surveys from NOW officers and NOW chapters. These records concern the establishment of the Schlesinger Library as NOW's records repository as well as determining what types of records were held by whom. Records are arranged chronologically.
Subseries F, Internal Politics (#16.3-16.9), contains correspondence, printed material, clippings, and completed surveys concerning internal disagreements in NOW. Included are records of the Majority Caucus, a group that successfully assumed leadership of NOW at the 1975 national conference. There also surveys sent by FAK polling NOW members about their opinions concerning a proposed by-law change extending office terms for NOW officers. Records are arranged chronologically.
Subseries G, Tully-Crenshaw Feminist Oral History Project (#16.10-16.14), contains correspondence and printed materials relating to the Tully-Crenshaw Feminist Oral History Project, which was initiated and funded in 1990 by Mary Jean Tully in honor of her mother, Maude Gresham Crenshaw, in conjunction with the Schlesinger Library, Radcliffe College. Records relate to FAK's interviews with Alice Rossi and Wilma Scott Heide, as well as her role on the advisory committee. Records are arranged chronologically.
Series V, FAK Workshops on U.S. Women's History (#16.15-18.6), contains correspondence, notes, and printed material from workshops run by FAK. Most of these workshops were arranged through her work with The Network, a nonprofit research and training organization in Andover, Massachusetts. FAK's workshops focused on using primary source material to teach high school students about the role of women throughout history. Records are arranged chronologically. However, when workshops were held annually, as was the National Endowment for the Humanities/Harvard Graduate School of Education workshop, materials are arranged chronologically by the date of the first workshop.
Series VI, Other Women's Organizations and Interest (#18.7-18.11), contains correspondence, notes, and printed material, concerning FAK's activities within the women's movement, excluding NOW and her workshops. Of particular interest is her folder concerning Jewish women.
Series VII, Memorabilia, (#19.1-19.8+), contains feminist buttons, scarves, and necklaces.
Folder headings are those of FAK unless otherwise noted; archivist's headings and notes are in square brackets. All printed material by or about FAK, as well as all printed material with annotations, has been kept in the collection. Other NOW publications and reports, except those created by FAK, were transferred to the NOW records in the Schlesinger Library. Non-NOW printed material produced by mainstream organizations and publications was discarded; leaflets and other ephemera of small, transient organizations were retained.
INVENTORY
- Series I. PERSONAL AND BIOGRAPHICAL
  - FAK resume, n.d., 1.1.
  - [Transcripts and printed material re: FAK education], 1955-1973 (scattered), 1.2.
  - [Birthday and Valentine's Day cards to FAK], 1965-1966, n.d., 1.3.
  - [Clippings re: FAK's work in women's movement], 1970, 1975-1976, 1.4.
  - [Press clippings re: FAK], 1984-1986., 1.5.
    Includes reference copy of photograph; original in #19.9.
  - [Contracts and correspondence re: FAK employment], 1973, 1975, 1.6.
  - [Correspondence and printed material re: FAK lectures], 1973-1976, 1981, 1984, 1.7.
  - Personal: contains copy of certificate of divorce from Zivon Cohen under Orthodox Hebrew Religious requirements and Hadassah membership certificate], 1977, n.d., 1.8.
- Series II. ARTICLES AND SPEECHES BY FAK
  - [FK writings re: women and psychoanalysis], 1974, n.d., 1.9.
  - [FAK affirmative response to question: should women's courses be centralized into a formal, separate women's studies department?], 1975, 1.10.
  - [FAK writings re: women in education, the ERA, and the women's movement], 1976, 1981-1982, n.d., 1.11.
  - "National Organization for Women: The Organization Whose Time had Come," Berkshire Conference of Women Historians, Vassar College, 1981, 1.12.
  - "The Integration of Women's History into School and Community," 1982, 1.13.
  - "Our First Struggle: National Organization for Women vs. the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission, 1965-1973," 1984, 1.14.
  - "Wilma Scott Heide: A Gadfly for Feminism" [draft and notes], 1984, 1.15.
  - "Wilma Scott Heide: A Gadfly for Feminism," 1985, 1.16.
  - "NOW and the Media: National Campaign of the 1970s," National Women's Studies Association, 1986, 1.17.
  - [FAK speech on women's history], 1986, 1.18.
  - "Betty Naomi Goldstein Friedan (1921-) Founder of the Second Feminist Movement" [notes, correspondence, draft], 1990, 1.19.
  - Betty Friedan essay [correspondence and draft, 1990, 1.20.
  - [Essays on Betty Friedan and Gloria Steinem: correspondence and drafts], 1990, 1.21.
  - "Gloria Steinem (1936- ) Founder and Leader of the Feminist Movement" [correspondence and draft], 1990, 1.22.
  - "The Feminist Scholar," n.d., 2.1.
  - "The National Organization for Women and the Search for Feminist Ideology," n.d., 2.2.
  - NOW speeches, n.d., 2.3.; See also #14.3.
  - "Popular Psychoanalysis and Women," n.d., 2.4.
- Series III. "THE NATIONAL ORGANIZATION FOR WOMEN: FROM THE FEMININE MYSTIQUE TO THE NATIONAL MOVEMENT, 1960-1974" [UNFINISHED BOOK]
  - Subseries A. Correspondence
    - (NOW book) Radcliffe support grant [correspondence, research proposals], 1978-1980, 2.5.
  - Subseries B. Drafts
    - Memo re: NOW book manuscript computer disk by Schlesinger staff member, n.d., 2.6.
    - Complete disk directories with notes re: file [printed and annotated by Schlesinger staff], n.d., 2.7.
    - NOW [book draft] table of contents, 1987, 1988, 1990, n.d., 2.8.
    - Chapter I text [binder 1 of 4], n.d., 2.9.
    - Chapter II text [binder 2 of 4], n.d., 2.10.
    - Chapter III text [binder 3 of 4], n.d., 2.11.
    - Chapter IV text [binder 4 of 4], n.d., 2.12.
    - [Partial text chapter III, 1 of 6], n.d., 2.13.
    - [Partial text chapter V, 2 of 6], n. d., 2.14.
    - [Partial text chapter VI, 3 of 6], n. d., 2.15.
    - [Partial text chapter X, 4 of 6], n. d., 2.16.
    - [Partial text chapter XI, 5 of 6], n. d., 2.17.
    - [Partial text chapter XII, 6 of 6], n. d., 2.18.
    - Chapter IV text, 1985-1986, 2.19.
    - Chapter VI text, 1985-1986, 3.1.
    - Chapter IX text, 1985-1986, 3.2.
    - Chapter X [text, printed from disks 7 and 13 by SL staff], n.d., 3.3.
    - "Employment in Public Sector (chapter X?) [text, printed from disk 13 by SL staff], n.d., 3.4.
    - "Employment in Higher Education" (chapter X) [text, printed from disk 13 by SL staff], n.d., 3.5.
    - Chapter XIII [text, printed from disk 13 by SL staff], n.d., 3.6.
    - Chapter I text, n.d., 3.7.
    - Chapter I [draft, notes], n.d., 3.8.
    - Chapter I [draft, notes re: equal pay], n.d., 3.9.
    - Chapter I [draft], n.d., 3.10.
    - Chapter II [draft, notes], n.d., 3.11.
    - Chapter II [text], n.d., 3.12.
    - Chapter III [text], n.d, 3.13.
    - Chapter III [draft], n.d., 3.14.
    - Chapter III [draft and notes], n.d., 3.15.
    - Chapter III [draft, notes], n.d., 3.16.
    - EEOC footnotes and draft [chapter III], n.d., 3.17.
    - Chapter III [text], n.d., 3.18.
    - Chapter III [draft], n.d., 4.1.
    - Chapter IV text, n.d., 4.2.
    - Chapter IV footnotes, n.d., 4.3.
    - Chapter IV [draft], n.d., 4.4.
    - Chapter IV [draft, notes], n.d., 4.5.
    - Chapter IV [draft, notes], n.d., 4.6.
    - Chapter IV [draft, notes], n.d., 4.7.
    - ERA campaign [chapter V, draft], n.d., 4.8.
    - Chapter V [draft], n.d., 4.9.
    - Chapter V [notes, partial text], n.d., 4.10.
    - Chapter V [draft re: second national NOW conference], n.d., 4.11.
    - ERA text [Chapter V, annotated draft], n.d., 4.12.
    - Chapter V text, n.d., 4.13.
    - Chapter V [footnotes], n.d., 4.14.
    - Chapter VI [notes, draft], n.d., 5.1.
    - Chapter VI text, n.d., 5.2.
    - Chapter VI [draft, notes], n.d., 5.3.
    - Chapter VII text, n.d., 5.4.
    - Chapter VII text, n.d., 5.5.
    - August 26 text [chapter VII, drafts], n.d., 5.6.
    - [Chapter VIII?, notes and text], n.d., 5.7.
    - By-laws [chapter VIII, annotated draft], n.d., 5.8.
    - Chapter IX [draft, notes], n.d., 5.9.
    - Chapter IX text, n.d., 5.10.
    - Chapter X [draft], n.d., 5.11.
    - Chapter X [draft, notes], n.d., 5.12.
    - Chapter XI text, n.d., 5.13.
    - Marriage and divorce [chapter XI, notes and text], n.d., 5.14.
    - Marriage and divorce [chapter XI, notes and draft], n.d., 5.15.
    - Chapter XI Older Women Task Force [text, notes], n.d., 5.16.
    - Older women [text, notes], n.d., 5.17.
    - Higher education [chapter XII, text and notes], n.d., 5.18.
    - Volunteering [chapter XII, notes, text], n.d., 6.1.
    - Chapter XII text, n.d., 6.2.
    - Chapter XII [draft, notes on rape], n.d., 6.3.
    - Chapter XIII: ERA [text and footnotes], n.d., 6.4.
    - NOW book footnotes, n.d., 6.5.
  - Subseries C. Oral Histories
    - NOW book correspondence [re: interviews; includes correspondence with Betty Berry, Aileen Hernandez, Karen DeCrow, Marguerite Rawalt, etc.], 1979-1982, 6.6-6.8.
    - [FAK notes re: tapes of interviews with early NOW officers], n.d., 6.9.
    - Tapes [NOW oral histories]-notes, n.d., 6.10.
    - Tapes: notes [NOW members], n.d., 6.11-6.12.
    - Permission forms [Schlesinger Library oral histories: Mary Lynn Myers, Jeane Bendorf, Muriel Fox], 1979, 6.13.
  - Subseries D. Research Notes
    - [Notes re: various topics], n.d. (5 folders), 6.14-7.2.
    - [Notes re: various topics, chapter additions], n.d., 7.3.
    - [Notes re: various topics, chapter IV], n.d., 7.4.
    - [Abortion, notes and correspondence], n.d., 7.5.
    - Abortion [notes], n.d., 7.6.
    - Abortion notes from secondary sources, n.d., 7.7.
    - Anti-feminist [notes], n.d., 7.8.
    - Compliance [notes and correspondence], n.d., 7.9.
    - Compliance: higher education 1971-1972 [notes], n.d., 7.10.
    - Education [notes], n.d., 7.11.
    - Employment [notes], n.d., 7.12.
    - Equal Employment Opportunity Commission (EEOC) compliance [notes], n.d., 7.13.
    - Equal Employment Opportunity Commission (EEOC) relations and actions [notes], n.d., 7.14.
    - Equal Employment Opportunity Commission (EEOC) [chapter III notes], n.d., 7.15.
    - Equal Rights Amendment (ERA) [notes], n.d., 7.16-7.21.
    - Equal Rights Amendment (ERA) [correspondence, notes, clippings], 1976-1978, 7.22.
    - Equal Rights Amendment (ERA) secondary analysis [notes, correspondence, printed material], 1981-1982, n.d., 7.23.
    - Family planning oral history [notes], n.d., 8.1.
    - Federal Communications Commission (FCC) [notes], n.d., 8.2-8.3.
    - Federal Communications Commission (FCC) and ATT [notes], n.d., 8.4.
    - Friedan and Heide collections [notes], n.d., 8.5.
    - League of Women Voters and NOW [notes], n.d., 8.6.
    - Marriage and divorce [notes], n.d., 8.7.
    - NOW actions [notes], n.d., 8.8-8.9
    - NOW administration [notes, correspondence], 1974, 8.10.
    - NOW administration [notes], n.d., 8.11-8.13.
    - NOW budgets [notes], n.d., 8.14.
    - NOW chapters [notes], n.d., 8.15-8.17.
    - NOW chronology [drafts, notes, correspondence], n.d., 8.18.
    - NOW day care [notes, printed material], 1972, n.d., 8.19.
    - NOW finances [notes], n.d., 8.20.
    - NOW financial matters 1973-1976 [notes], n.d., 8.21.
    - NOW founding [notes], n.d., 8.22-8.23.
    - NOW fundraising [notes], n.d., 8.24.
    - NOW growth [notes], n.d., 8.25.
    - NOW legal [notes, correspondence], 1976, n.d., 8.26.
    - NOW legal cases [notes], n.d., 9.1.
    - NOW Legislative Vice President 1969-1972 [notes], n.d., 9.2.
    - NOW members [notes], n.d., 9.3.
    - Membership materials [notes], n.d., 9.4.
    - Membership recruiting 1966-1968 [notes], n.d., 9.5.
    - NOW national board minutes [notes], n.d., 9.6.
    - NOW national conference 1968 [notes], n.d., 9.7.
    - NOW national conference 1969 [notes], n.d., 9.8.
    - NOW national conference 1970 [notes], n.d., 9.9.
    - NOW national conferences 1971-1974 [notes], n.d., 9.10
    - NOW policies [notes, includes national board member list], n.d., 9.11.
    - NOW policy manuals [notes], n.d., 9.12.
    - NOW politics [notes], n.d., 9.13.
    - NOW and the press [notes], n.d., 9.14.
    - NOW and the press 1973-1974 [notes], n.d., 9.15.
    - NOW public relations [notes], n.d., 9.16-9.17.
    - NOW publications [notes], n.d., 9.18.
    - NOW publications: resource lists [notes], n.d., 9.19.
    - NOW regions [notes], n.d., 9.20.
    - NOW spinoffs [notes], n.d., 9.21-9.22.
    - NOW Task Force on the Arts [notes], n.d., 9.23.
    - NOW Task Force: Compliance [notes], n.d., 9.24-9.25.
    - NOW Task Force: Credit [notes], n.d., 9.26.
    - NOW Task Force: Image [notes], n.d., 9.27-9.28.
    - NOW Task Force: Labor [notes], n.d., 9.29.
    - NOW Task Force: Marriage and Divorce [notes], n.d., 9.30.
    - NOW Task Force: Masculine Mystique [notes], n.d., 10.1.
    - NOW Task Force policy [notes], n.d., 10.2.
    - NOW Task Force: Politics [notes], n.d., 10.3.
    - NOW Task Force: Poverty [notes], n.d., 10.4-10.5.
    - NOW Task Force: Rape [notes], n.d., 10.6.
    - NOW Task Force: Sexuality and Lesbianism [notes], n.d., 10.7.
    - NOW Task Force: Women and Health [notes], n.d., 10.8.
    - NOW Task Force: Women and Religion [notes], n.d., 10.9.
    - NOW LDEF [correspondence, notes], n.d., 10.10.
    - Presidential election 1972 [notes], n.d., 10.11.
    - Second Wave Feminism: the Kennedy Commission [notes], n.d., 10.12.
    - Second Wave founding [notes], n.d., 10.13.
    - Second Wave Feminism from secondary sources [notes], n.d., 10.14.
    - Second Wave Feminism theory readings [notes], n.d., 10.15.
    - Women and credit [notes], n.d., 10.16.
    - [Women's movement in the] press [notes], n.d., 10.17.
    - Women's Strike: August 26, 1970 [notes], n.d., 10.18-10.21.
    - Women's studies books [notes], n.d., 10.22.
    - [Women's studies] general reviews of attitude polls [notes], n.d., 10.23.
    - [Women's studies] secondary references [notes, correspondence], n.d., 10.24.
- Series IV. NATIONAL ORGANIZATION FOR WOMEN-RELATED
  - Subseries A. NOW General Correspondence
    - [NOW correspondence], 1973-1974, 11.1.
    - [NOW correspondence], 1973-1980, 1987, 11.2.
    - NOW correspondence, 1974-1976, 1979, 1982-1984, 11.3.
    - NOW correspondence, 1974, 1977, 11.4.
  - Subseries B. Eastern Region
    - [NOW eastern region transmittal of funds (forms)], 1972, 11.5.
    - NOW Eastern Regional Convention [reports], 1972, 11.6.
    - [NOW Eastern Regional Convention: receipts, vouchers, paid bills], 1973, 11.7.
    - [NOW Eastern Regional Convention: financial records, correspondence with Jo-Ann Evans Gardner], 1973, 11.8.
    - Eastern Regional Convention [correspondence, notes, printed material], 1973, 11.9.
    - [NOW Eastern Regional Conventions printed material], 1973-1974, 11.10.
    - NOW chapter charters [correspondence], 1972-1973, 11.11.
    - How to kits sent [forms and lists], 1972-1973, 11.12.
    - State coordinator [correspondence], 1973, 11.13.
    - State structure [printed material, notes], 1973, 11.14.
    - NOW Eastern expenses, 1973-1974, 11.15.
    - State coordinating meetings [correspondence, notes], 1973-1974, 11.16.
    - NOW Eastern Region [Jacqueline Ceballos correspondence], 1973, 11.17.
    - Eastern Region correspondence [with Jo-Ann Evans Gardner], 1973-1974, 11.18.
    - [Eastern] Regional correspondence [notes, printed material re: Eastern Regional Conference], 1974, 11.19.
    - Eastern Region [correspondence], 1974-1975, 11.20.
    - NOW Connecticut [correspondence, clippings, printed material], 1972, 12.1.
    - NOW Delaware [correspondence, printed material], 1972-1973, 12.2.
    - NOW Massachusetts [correspondence, printed], 1972-1973, 12.3.
    - [Massachusetts] NOW elections [annotated printed material], 1986-1987, 12.4.
    - NOW Lexington, Massachusetts [correspondence], 1972, 12.5.
    - NOW Mid-east New Jersey and other New Jersey organizations [correspondence, clippings, printed material created by Jacqueline Ceballos], 1972, 12.6.
    - NOW New Jersey [correspondence, printed material, clippings created by Jacqueline Ceballos], 1972-1973, 12.7.
    - NOW New Jersey [correspondence, printed material], 1973, 12.8.